Finding Aid for Carl Ernest Schmidt papers, 1892-1935
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Carl Ernest Schmidt papers
1892-1935
Schmidt, Carl Ernest, 1856-1934.
85387 Aa 2; AC
Detroit German-American business; scrapbooks containing a variety of printed material, photographs, handwritten accounts of sentiments and occasions, and hand-drawn ink illustrations.
15 volumes in 3 boxes
1 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (donor no. 6902 ) was donated in March 1983 by Mrs. Elizabeth W. Wyborski, daughter of Nicholas J. Shorn, Schmidt’s business manager and his successor as president of Schmidt’s tannery business.
The collection is open to research.
Carl Ernest Schmidt (1856-1934) was a successful Detroit businessman prominent in the German-American society of the turn of the century. He was the eldest son of Traugott Schmidt, who had emigrated from Thuringa, Germany, and Wilhelmina Beck, who was originally from Pennsylvania. Carl Schmidt was born in Detroit, which was his main residence throughout his life. His longest leave from his native state was during his schooling, which took him to various schools in Germany, from 1870 to 1875.
When he returned home he began learning his father's trade, tanning. The father and son became business partners in the Schmidt tannery, which became very prosperous because of its development of a process by which calf skin is tanned into white leather. In 1897 Traugott Schmidt died, leaving his son to carry on the tannery business, which was soon renamed Carl E. Schmidt and Company.
It was also in the 1890's that Carl Schmidt began to acquire his prominence in local and state politics. From 1892 to 1894 he was a member of the board of police commissioners of Detroit. In 1897 Schmidt was encouraged by some of the leading Republicans to run in the Detroit mayoral elections for 1898. He declined the opportunity. Instead, he became a member of the state Board of Arbitration and Mediation, in 1897-1898.
In 1907 Schmidt was appointed to the state Board of Forest Inquiry. This last appointment is reflective of his love and concern for Michigan's natural resources.
Besides his commitment to the reforestation of Michigan, Schmidt was also interested in outdoor recreation and farming. He built a lodge on some property that he owned in Iosco County, in northern Michigan. He named this isolated retreat "Walhalla" and it was here that Schmidt entertained many of his friends, especially other prominent German-Americans. Hunting, target-shooting, boating, horse-back riding, and hiking were the main outdoor diversions for Schmidt and his guests. The automobile and train trips to and from the retreat were considered adventures in themselves. Inside the lodge, at night or in inclement weather, the visiting party would be entertained by cards and board games. Schmidt was also a major investor in a commercial resort area in Alcona County, called Greenbush. The most advertised activity there was tobogganing.
Farming was yet another Schmidt preoccupation. Along with his Walhalla retreat Schmidt owned over 6,000 acres in Iosco and Alcona counties. A portion of this area became Schmidt's "Serradella Farms," where, from the early 1900's to the mid 1930's, Schmidt oversaw a number of agricultural experiments. He had intended to determine which crops could be successfully raised in the sandy soil that prevailed on his property. However, the breeding of Holstein cattle eventually became the main endeavor at Serradella. During the Depression operations at the farm were ended.
Schmidt was an active promoter of respect and pride in the German heritage that was shared by German-Americans. This allegiance to his ethnic background was demonstrated by Schmidt's leadership roles in the German-American community. He was involved particularly in the Steuben Society of America and the Concord Society of America.
The Carl E. Schmidt collection consists of sixteen volumes of scrapbooks documenting the wide scope of Schmidt's interests. These scrapbooks were compiled and numbered by Schmidt himself, although some of the explanatory text was added by a friend, Dr. Tobias Sigel, who was himself a German immigrant and prominent citizen of Detroit. The scrapbooks are filled with a variety of printed material, photographs, handwritten accounts of sentiments and occasions, and hand-drawn ink illustrations. Much of the scrapbooks' text is in German, including many clippings from German language newspapers. The illustrations in Volume II are particularly attractive. They are hand-drawn red and black ink illustrations of fanciful, legendary themes relating to Walhalla.
The following inventory is a general guide to the contents of each volume. For those scrapbooks that were paginated by Schmidt, specific sections of special interest have been noted in the inventory. Volume 2 also has its own, original index. There is one corresponding folder for each of thirteen of the volumes. These folders contain loose items removed from volumes one through eleven, thirteen, and fourteen.
As the inventory shows, Schmidt was most thorough in documenting his recreational and farming interests, and his political activity in Detroit, at the state level, and in the German-American community. There is, however, very little information about his tannery business.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Michigan--Iosco County.; Automobile travel.; Detroit (Mich.). Police Dept.; Detroit (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Forest fires--Michigan.; Forests and forestry--Michigan.; Game and game birds.; German Americans--Michigan.; Hunting--Michigan.; Iosco County (Mich.); Michigan--Description and travel.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1891-1900.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1901-1910.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1911-1920.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1921-1930.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1931-1940.; Michigan--Social life and customs--19th century.; Michigan--Social life and customs--20th century.; Michigan. State Board of Arbitration and Mediation.; Michigan. Commission of Inquiry, Tax Lands and Forestry.; Pacifism.; Recreation--Michigan--Iosco County.; Resorts--Michigan--Iosco County.; Travelers.; Voyages and travels.; World War, 1914-1918.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Agriculture--Michigan.; Alcona County (Mich.); Animals.; Au Sable (Mich.); Barns.; Boats.; Carts and wagons.; Cedar Lake (Alcona County and Iosco County, Mich.); Dams.; Drawings.; Dwellings.; Estates--Michigan--Oscoda.; Farms.; Fires--Michigan--Au Sable--1911.; Fires--Michigan--Oscoda--1911.; Forestry.; German Americans--Michigan.; Horses.; Hunting--Michigan.; Interiors.; Iosco County (Mich.); Labadie, Jo, 1850-1933.; Leather industry.; Oscoda (Mich.)--Estates.; Oscoda (Mich.)--Fires--1911.; Roads--1901-1910.; Schmidt, Carl Ernest, 1856-1934.; Sleds and sleighs.; Walhalla (Estate: Oscoda, Mich.)
Contributors:
Labadie, Jo, 1850-1933.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Biographical Material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks
  - Unnumbered volume, 1892-1898 (Box 1)
    General subjects include: Schmidt's resignation from Detroit Police Board Committee in 1894 Schmidt as Pingree's preferred successor for mayor of Detroit in 1897 Death of Traugott Schmidt, Carl Schmidt's father, in 1897
  - Volume 1, 1905-1906 (Box 1)
    General subjects include: Travel to and around Walhalla Entertainment at Walhalla, including hunting, card games, target shooting
    Of special interest: Excursions to Walhalla "The Ride on the Locomotive," p. 22-24 "A Northern Trip," p. 41-44 (printed article) Sketch of land and distribution of seeds at Walhalla, p. 135
  - Volume 2 with index, 1907-1908 (Box 1)
    General subjects include: Travel to and around Walhalla Entertainment at Walhalla, including hunting, boating excursions, dining, card games German-language poetry
    Of special interest: Tree-planting expeditions at Walhalla, p. 3-36, 42-90 Winter junket to Walhalla, p. 106-143
  - Volume 3, 1908-1909 (Box 1)
    General subjects include: Travel to and around Walhalla Entertainment at Walhalla, including ice boating, card games, horse-back riding, boating German-language poetry Conservation in Michigan
    Of special interest: Promotion of reforestation in Michigan Schmidt appointed by Governor Warner to develop a comprehensive system of reforestation, p. 45 Trip with Jo Labadie, photos, p. 127-138, and manuscript by Labadie, in volume 3 folder
  - Volume 4, 1911-1912 (Box 1)
    General subjects include: Travel to and around Walhalla Entertainment at Walhalla, including ice boating, board games, hiking German and English-language poetry about Walhalla Correspondence about Walhalla
    Of special interest: Excursions to Walhalla Automobile trip from Detroit to Walhalla, p. 102-120 Fire aftermath in Au Sable and Oscoda, p. 68-95
  - Volume 5, 1912-1916 (Box 1)
    General subjects include: Detroit municipal issues Schmid's leather company Pacifist sentiment among German-Americans Conservation in Michigan
    Of special interest: Schmidt's criticism of the lumberjack, p. 20-22 Advertisement for Schmidt leather goods, p. 26-27 Schmidt's defense of the Kaiser in 1914, p. 126 Schmidt's interest in municipal ownership of the street railway system, p. 138-139 Resolution of German-Americans demanding pacifism on part of the U. S. government, back inside cover of scrapbook
  - Volume 6, 1916-1930 (Box 2)
    General subjects include: Automobile touring in Michigan Farming at Serradella German-Americans' reaction to U. S. participation in World War I Schmidt's funding of Base Hospital No. 36, A.E.F., France
    Of special interest: The American Independence Conference, held in Chicago, on September 30, 1916, p. 46-51 Minutes and statements Schmidt's leadership in the German-American move against Roosevelt, p. 57 Jo Labadie's poem against the war, p. 63
  - Volume 7, 1914-1922 (Box 2)
    General subjects include: German-Americans' reaction to U. S. participation in World War I Prohibition Walhalla Schmidt's travels in Germany, 1921
    Of special interest: Schmidt's account of the war, and its affect on his writing, p. 2-6 Photographs of Schmidt's tannery (?), p. 74-1/2-75
  - Volume 8, 1920-1925 (Box 2)
    General subjects include: Serradella Farm Greenbush Inn German-American organizations Steuben Society of America Concord Society of America
  - Volume 9, 1921-1925 (Box 2)
    General subjects include: Carl Schmidt's visit to Germany, 1921 Steuben Society of America
  - Volume 10, 1922-1931 (Box 2)
    General subjects include: Detroit German-Americans' "Jahrmarkt" in 1922 (fund-raising event for needy German children) Greenbush resort
  - Volume 11, undated (Box 3)
    General subjects include: Walhalla excursions Germania "Kegel Klubs"
  - Volume 12, undated (Box 3)
    General subjects include: Winter excursions to Greenbush
  - Volume 13, 1921-1934 (Box 3)
    Walhalla Guest Book
  - Volume 14, 1906-1935 (Box 3)
    General. subjects include: Reforestation in Michigan Carl Schmidt's death, 1934
  - Unnumbered volume, 1905-1913 (Volume 1)
    General subjects include: Photographs of Walhalla lodge and farm scenes Au Sable River